<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/xslt/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xml:lang="EN-us"><title>Saxon Chronicles</title><subtitle>(in a Norman style)</subtitle><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/atom/norm.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/atom.xml</id><updated>2026-02-04T17:02:41.14800024Z</updated><author><name>Norm Tovey-Walsh</name></author><entry><title>Maven repository</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2026/02/04-maven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2026/02/04-maven.html</id><published>2026-02-04T17:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2026/02/04-maven.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>I’ve posted about our Maven repository
<a href="/norm/2020/10/29-maven.html">before</a> (and
<a href="/norm/2020/10/02-maven.html">before that</a>).
It’s where we publish our commercial products, Saxon PE and Saxon EE, accessible
via Maven. It’s moved since we first announced it, it’s now at
<a href="https://maven.saxonica.com/">https://maven.saxonica.com</a>.</p>

<p>You can use it by configuring your build system to include our
repository. For example, in a Kotlin Gradle build script, like this:</p>

<pre><code>repositories {
    maven { url = uri("https://maven.saxonica.com/maven") }
}</code></pre>

<p>Then you can use Maven coordinates to get the libraries. For example, like
this:</p>

<pre><code>dependencies {
  implementation("com.saxonica:Saxon-EE:12.9")
}</code></pre>

<p>It’s been running without incident for just over five years now, so I think
we can stop calling it experimental. It wasn’t clear when we first put it up if
just hosting it on some static web pages would be sufficient. It appears to be.
I’m confident that whatever benefits we’d see from running an actual artifact
repository system would be outweighed by the complexity of doing so.</p>

<p>Our open source product, Saxon HE, is published in our repository for
completeness, but it’s also available as usual through
<a href="https://search.maven.org/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE">Maven Central</a>.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Two steps forward…</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2026/02/04-qt4cg.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2026/02/04-qt4cg.html</id><published>2026-02-04T12:30:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2026/02/04-qt4cg.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Two steps forward…</h1>

<p><a href="https://qt4cg.org/">QT4CG</a>, the commuity group developing the
4.0 versions of XPath, XQuery, XSLT, and related specifications, has been hard
at work now for more than three years. We just had our 151st meeting.</p>

<p>It’s a large body of work. Lots of changes have been requested: there are
2,437 issues today, with 70 remaining open. Lots of changes have been proposed,
drafted, reviewed and accepted (or rejected, as the case may be): there are
2,441 pull requests today, with 12 currently open. We’ve added tests to the test
suite and implementations are underway.</p>

<p>I’m pleased, in my role as chair of the group, to announce that we’ve
published our first set of “<a href="https://qt4cg.org/#drafts-2026-01-28">stable drafts</a>”.
These <em>are not</em> final specifications, but they do reflect the consensus of
the group near the end of January, 2026. The
<a href="https://qt4cg.org/#speclist">current drafts</a> are still the place to look for the most
recent consensus positions.</p>

<p>Publishing dated, stable drafts serves a couple of purposes. First and
foremost, it gives users and implementors a stable set of documents to refer to.
As Saxonica works towards a Saxon 13 release, we’ll be able to make assertions
about what features we do (or do not) support, confident that those features
won’t change in the draft we’re referencing. Those features may still change, of
course, but we can say we implemented against a stable draft.</p>

<p>It’s also a strong signal to the community that we think we’re making
progress towards the finish line. </p>

<p><em>Yes, but when will you be done</em>, I hear you ask?</p>

<p>In practical terms, when the group thinks the specifications are complete and
coherent, and when it agrees to stop changing them. That’s a
social engineering issue, not a technical one. Specifications, perhaps even more than code,
are governed by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ninety%E2%80%93ninety_rule">90/90 rule</a>:
the first 90% of drafting takes 90% of the time, the remaining 10% of drafting takes the
other 90% of the time.</p>

<p>Personally, I’ll be <em>very</em> surprised if we finish in 2026 (that remaining 10%
really is <em>a lot</em> of work), and surprised [if somewhat less <em>very</em>], if
we don’t finish in 2027. </p> </div></content></entry><entry><title>Windows Help?</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/11/03-windows.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/11/03-windows.html</id><published>2025-11-03T17:45:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/11/03-windows.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>I’m asking for help, but first, a little background. Saxon 10.x is the last Saxon release that
supported Microsoft .NET Framework. The Saxon 11 and 12 releases only run on
.NET Core. But we still have customers with applications that need .NET
Framework and Microsoft continues to support it on Windows.</p>

<p>We’d like to be able to provide a .NET Framework version of SaxonCS built
from the current sources. In principle, this should be possible because we build
SaxonCS by transpiling Java source code to C# source code (mixed in with some
hand-written C#).</p>

<p>I undertook to see if I could make that work. I took a SaxonCS 12.x build and
attempted to compile it with .NET Framework. I worked back and forth on the
transpiler and on the generated C# code until I got something that compiled.</p>

<p>But a simple
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/12.99.99/identity.xsl">identity transformation</a>
fails with an <code>AccessViolationException</code>:</p>

<pre><code>
C:\tmp&gt;.\SaxonCS transform -s:\tmp\identity.xsl -xsl:\tmp\identity.xsl
file:/C:/tmp/identity.xsl
Processing item &lt;xsl:stylesheet/&gt; ::
Processing item @exclude-result-prefixes ::
System.AccessViolationException: Attempted to read or write protected memory. This is often an indication that other memory is corrupt.
   at Saxon.Hej.trans.rules.ShallowCopyRuleSet.process(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\trans\rules\ShallowCopyRuleSet.cs:line 93
   at Saxon.Hej.trans.Mode.applyTemplates(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\trans\Mode.cs:line 186
   at Saxon.Hej.trans.rules.ShallowCopyRuleSet.process(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\trans\rules\ShallowCopyRuleSet.cs:line 58
   at Saxon.Hej.trans.Mode.applyTemplates(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\trans\Mode.cs:line 186
   at Saxon.Hej.expr.instruct.ApplyTemplates.ApplyTemplatesPackage.processLeavingTail() in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\expr\instruct\ApplyTemplates.cs:line 243
   at Saxon.Hej.trans.Mode.applyTemplates(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\trans\Mode.cs:line 153
   at Saxon.Hej.trans.XsltController.applyTemplates(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\trans\XsltController.cs:line 206
   at Saxon.Hej.s9api.Xslt30Transformer.applyTemplates(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\s9api\Xslt30Transformer.cs:line 76
   at Saxon.Hej.Transform.processFile(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\Transform.cs:line 805
   at Saxon.Hej.Transform.doTransform(...) in ...generated\Saxon\Hej\Transform.cs:line 547
Fatal error during transformation: AccessViolationException: Attempted to read or write protected memory. This is often an indication that other memory is corrupt.
Exiting with code 2
</code></pre>

<p>No amount of effort on my part has enabled me to find out where that problem occurs, or why.
In the debugger, it’s on a perfectly harmless looking statement and taking one step forward
immediately crashes the process.
We got a Windows consultant (he’s helping us with some performance analysis, but he knows
a lot more about Windows than I do) to take a look.</p>

<p>Thing is, it works on his machine. My build works on his machine, his build fails on my machine.
And those builds fail on some other machines too.</p>

<p>I expressed some frustration (*cough*) at a team meeting and threatened to just pull the plug
on the whole thing. But, we seem to be so close…</p>

<p>Mike said, “why don’t we ask the internet”. So that’s what I’m doing. If you’re a Windows
developer, you can get the entirely janky
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/12.99.99/SaxonCS-net481-12-99-99.zip">SaxonCS-net481-12-99-99.zip</a>
build and run it through your favorite debugging tools. If you can
show me what I’ve done wrong, I would be ever so grateful. (To the tune of a free
individual license, if you like.)</p>

<p>A few points about the build:</p>

<ul>
<li>It’s a .NET Framework 4.8.1 Windows/X86 build.</li>
<li>It’s really janky; it’s from C# source code that I’ve hacked on mercilessly.</li>
<li>It emits a bunch of random debugging messages.</li>
<li>It won’t read a license file and there’s no way to enable licensable features.</li>
<li>Some commands do succeed, but that identity transform fails on some machines.</li>
<li>It should go without saying, but I’m going to say it anyway, do not use that
build for anything except testing.</li>
</ul>

<p>The failure isn’t related to the version of Windows (at least not the major
version number). We aren’t able to see any obvious differences in the SDKs
installed or the build tools used between machines where it succeeds and where
it fails.</p>

<p>Can you:</p>

<ol>
<li>Explain why it succeeds on some machines and fails on others?</li>
<li>Tell me what to change so that it will always succeed?</li>
</ol>

<p>Clues most humbly solicited, if it’s the sort of puzzle that interests you.
I recognize that not being able to provide the source code and build environment 
is a serious limitation.</p>

<p>If it helps, here are the build commands I used:</p>

<pre><code>dotnet restore SaxonCS.sln --verbosity Normal -p:Configuration=Release -p:Platform="Any CPU"
dotnet build SaxonCS.sln --verbosity Normal /nodereuse:false --no-restore \
       -p:Version=12.99.99 -p:PackageVersion=12.99.99 -p:Configuration=Release \
       -p:Platform="Any CPU" -p:DefineConstants=EE
dotnet publish SaxonCS.sln -r win-x64 --self-contained true -p:PublishSingleFile=false \
       -p:Version=12.99.99 -p:PackageVersion=12.99.99 -p:Configuration=Release \
       -p:Platform="Any CPU"</code></pre>

<p>🤞</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Preparing for Saxon 13</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/10/15-saxon13.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/10/15-saxon13.html</id><published>2025-10-15T12:15:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/10/15-saxon13.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>We’ve made a couple of Saxon 12 releases where we (once intentionally, once
accidentally) built the Java release without support for JDK 8. Users
noticed.</p>

<p>We’re starting to think about Saxon 13 and we’re definitely planning to move
the minimum Java version forward. There are still a few years left in JDK 8
extended service support, but our build tools are beginning to issue deprecation
warnings for it.</p>

<p>JDK 8 was released more than a decade ago. There have been a lot of Java
language improvements in the intervening years and we’re starting to take
advantage of some of them.</p>

<p>It makes sense to choose a “long term service” (LTS) release. We’ll want to
avoid changing the version during maintenance releases. The <a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/technologies/java-se-support-roadmap.html">Java
LTS releases</a> are 11, 17, 21, and 25. Premier support for 11 has already
ended and version 25 was only released last month, that’s probably too
aggressive.</p>

<p>That leaves 17 or 21. We’re leaning towards Java 17, but we’d welcome any
thoughts you might have.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 12.9!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/09/saxon-12.9.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/09/saxon-12.9.html</id><published>2025-09-12T17:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/09/saxon-12.9.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 12.9!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 12.9 maintenance release has been published. This is a maintenance
release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that fixes a number of
issues that have been raised since 12.8 was released.</p>

<p>Saxon 12.9 was released on 12 September 2025. This release has been uploaded to the
usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub, and Maven, PyPi, and NuGet.
SaxonCS 12.9 is built with .NET 8.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the issue trackers
for
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;set_filter=1&amp;amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=c&amp;amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=105&amp;amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;amp;group_by=&amp;amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonJ and SaxonCS</a> or
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=c&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=106&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonC</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/12.9">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonC releases for HE, PE, and EE are also available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>Python wheels for SaxonC (HE, PE, and EE) are available from
<a href="https://pypi.org/user/saxonica/">PyPI</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is available from our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<h2>Issues resolved in SaxonJ</h2>

<p>This release fixes about twenty issues in SaxonJ and SaxonCS.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6893">6893</a>
    Corrected an error in the Gizmo help messages</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6892">6892</a>
    Fixed expression tree corruption after a rewrite optimization</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6891">6891</a>
    Fixed an issue with regex flags when using the Java regex engine</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6889">6889</a>
    Fixed an infinite loop when using trace listeners with try/catch and function variables</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6887">6887</a>
    Added synchronization to avoid an exception</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6883">6883</a>
    Corrected an error where the xsl:catch errors attribute didn’t accept EQNames</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6881">6881</a>
    Fixed an exception when using 'position() eq last()' with no context item</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6878">6878</a>
    Changed <code>parse-xml()</code> so that validation is never attempted</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6866">6866</a>
    Corrected a namespace handling error when using the Domino tree model</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6864">6864</a>
    Implemented a performance improvement for slash expressions and simple step expressions</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6863">6863</a>
    Corrected a navigation error in snapshot trees</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6860">6860</a>
    Corrected errors in how character maps were handled when using adaptive serialization</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6858">6858</a>
    Improved error location information for some exceptions</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6856">6856</a>
    Corrected an API error distinguishing between empty maps and empty sequences</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6840">6840</a>
    Fixed an incorrect type inference for call on abs()</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6824">6824</a>
    Fixed an error in how the retained static context is managed</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6818">6818</a>
    Corrected an exception that could arise if attempting to serialize a free-standing attribute</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6809">6809</a>
    Fixed the line number of errors in a free-standing XPath expression</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6805">6805</a>
    Fixed a streaming bug related to comment handling</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6799">6799</a>
    Fixed an exception on number-formatter option function of xml-to-json using xsl:value-of</li>
</ul>

<h2>Issues in SaxonC</h2>

<p>This release includes a number of improvements in memory management
and support for multi-threaded execution.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6897">6897</a>
    Fixed a bug where the <code>XQueryProcessor.setQueryBaseURI()</code> method had no effect</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6885">6885</a>
    Corrected a Python bug where getting the parent of the root node threw an exception</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6880">6880</a>
    Fixed a bug where <code>XsltExexutable.getXslMessages()</code> did not release memory</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6879">6879</a>
    Fixed a bug where <code>XsltExecutable.callFunctionReturningValue()</code> did not release memory</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6859">6859</a>
    Corrected an error where <code>saxonc-core.h</code> header was missing from source zip</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6843">6843</a>
    Fixed a bug where <code>XsltExecutable.clone()</code> did not work correctly with multiple threads</li>
</ul>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 12.9, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Serving and styling XML on the web</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/08/21-styling-xml.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/08/21-styling-xml.html</id><published>2025-08-21T11:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/08/21-styling-xml.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>For more than twenty years, it’s been possible to serve XML documents on the
web, making them available to applications as well-formed XML and to humans as
nicely formatted web pages. This is a win-win scenario for many users, but the
<a href="https://whatwg.org/">WHATWG</a> is moving aggressively to take away
this long-standing web capability.</p>

<p>The WHATWG is moving to deprecate, and then remove, native support for XSLT
in the browser. It’s XSLT that provides the formatted web page from an XML
document. Faced with the prospect of losing native support for XSLT in the
browser, a natural question our users ask is “can we use SaxonJS instead?” The
answer is yes, but it’s a little bit complicated.</p>

<p>Let’s step back for a moment and look (broadly) at how the web works and what’s
actually going on under the hood.</p>

<p>For the application, this is simple: it requests the web page; it gets back a
document with an <code>application/xml</code> media type; it parses it; and it does what it
does with the XML data. Job done.</p>

<p>For the human user reading the page with a web browser, there’s a little bit
more going on.</p>

<ol type="1">
<li>The browser requests the page.</li>
<li>It gets back an <code>application/xml</code> page and parses it.</li>
<li>If the page has an <code>xml-stylesheet</code> processing instruction:
  <ol type="a">
    <li>The browser loads the stylesheet that the processing instruction points to;</li>
    <li>if it’s an XSLT stylesheet, it transforms the XML document with the stylesheet;</li>
    <li>and it displays the transformed result to the reader</li>
  </ol>
</li>
</ol>
   
<p>(If the document doesn’t have an <code>xml-stylesheet</code> processing instruction, the
browser just displays the raw XML in some way or another. How useful this is
depends on the browser and the XML markup.)</p>

<p>It’s the fact that the browser recognizes, and responds to, the
<code>xml-stylesheet</code> processing instruction that starts the process off.
This document:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;?xml-stylesheet href="/xslt/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl"?&gt;
&lt;feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
      xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
      xml:lang="EN-us"&gt;
   &lt;title&gt;Saxonica Weblogs&lt;/title&gt;
   &lt;link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/&gt;
   &lt;link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/&gt;
   &lt;id&gt;https://blog.saxonica.com/atom.xml&lt;/id&gt;
   …
</code></pre>

<p>Will be styled with the <code>/xslt/atom.xsl</code> stylesheet before being
displayed because the <code>xml-stylesheet</code> processing intruction on the
first line tells it to.</p>

<p>If WHATWG takes away that capability, the XML document becomes inert.</p>

<p>The challenge that we, as users, face is to find some place to stand from
which we can begin the styling process. The more common SaxonJS use case begins
with an HTML browser page, and it’s obvious how to bootstrap a JavaScript
application from there.</p>

<p>Luckily, for the moment at least, the browser will run scripts that are
embedded in the XML using the <code>script</code> element in the HTML namespace.
So that’s where we can stand. If we remove the processing instruction and add
script lines, we can run SaxonJS:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
      xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
      xml:lang="EN-us"&gt;

   &lt;script xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
           type="text/javascript" src="/js/saxon-js/SaxonJS2.rt.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
   &lt;script xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;
      SaxonJS.transform({
        stylesheetLocation: "/xslt/atom.sef.json",
        initialTemplate: "main"
      }, "async");
   &lt;/script&gt;

   &lt;title&gt;Saxonica Weblogs&lt;/title&gt;
   &lt;link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/&gt;
   &lt;link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/&gt;
   &lt;id&gt;https://blog.saxonica.com/atom.xml&lt;/id&gt;
   …
</code></pre>

<p>I’m not going to try to give a SaxonJS tutorial here, but in brief: the first
script loads SaxonJS; the second script loads the <em>compiled</em> version of the stylesheet,
<code>/xslt/atom.sef.json</code>, and runs the template named “<code>main</code>”.
</p>

<p>The <code>/xslt/atom.xsl</code> stylesheet can remain mostly the same as the
one you’re using currently in the browser except, of course, that you can now
use XSLT 3.0 features.
One complication is that you have to add two templates to your XSLT
stylesheet. The easiest way to do that is by placing these lines in a file
called <code>saxonjs-templates.xsl</code>:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
                xmlns:ixsl="http://saxonica.com/ns/interactiveXSLT"
                version="3.0"&gt;

&lt;xsl:template name="main"&gt;
  &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="ixsl:page()" mode="format-feed"/&gt;
&lt;/xsl:template&gt;

&lt;xsl:template match="/" mode="format-feed"&gt;
  &lt;xsl:result-document href="?." method="ixsl:replace-content"&gt;
    &lt;xsl:apply-templates select="."/&gt;
  &lt;/xsl:result-document&gt;
&lt;/xsl:template&gt;

&lt;/xsl:stylesheet&gt;</code></pre>

<p>The first template is the one that is run from the script in the XML
document. It doesn’t have to be named “<code>main</code>” but the names used in
both places have to be the same. This template takes the current page, the XML
document, and processes it in the <code>format-feed</code> mode.</p>

<p>The second template just uses <code>xsl:apply-templates</code> on itself to
process the XML document in the default mode, this will run the rest of your
stylesheet, <code>/xslt/atom.xsl</code>. Surrounding that call to
apply-templates is an <code>xsl:result-document</code> instruction that will have the effect
of replacing the current document with the styled result. That’s what “<code>?.</code>” and
<code>ixsl:replace-content</code> achieve.</p>

<p>Use <code>xsl:include</code> at the top of <code>/xslt/atom.xsl</code> to include
the contents of <code>saxonjs-templates.xsl</code>:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
                xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
                xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" 
                exclude-result-prefixes="#all"
                version="3.0"&gt;
&lt;xsl:include href="saxonjs-templates.xsl"/&gt;
&lt;xsl:output method="html" html-version="5"
            encoding="utf-8" indent="no"/&gt;
  ...
</code></pre>

<p>I’ve taken the opportunity to update the version and the
<code>xsl:output</code> method as well, since we’re now using XSLT 3.0 not 1.0.</p>

<p>To compile <code>/xslt/atom.xsl</code> to <code>/xslt/atom.sef.json</code>,
you can use Saxon-EE or you can install SaxonJS on Node.js and use node,
something like this:</p>

<pre><code>node xslt3.js -xsl:xslt/atom.xsl -export:xslt/atom.sef.json -nogo -ns:##html5</code></pre>

<p>(Depending on your platform, you might have to quote or escape the hashes in <code>-ns:##html5</code>)</p>

<p>That all works. This is an unexplored use case; it’s clear that we could make
it a little simpler by adding some options to the <code>SaxonJS.transform</code>
method.</p>

<p>Not everyone will find this situation wholly satisfying. It’s a little bit
complicated and it introduces an edit-compile-debug cycle into your workflow. You
can’t just use the plain old XSL stylesheet; you have to use the compiled
version. The compiler comes with Saxon-EE and is also available for free on
Node.js, but they aren’t open source.</p>

<p>Other approaches that could be used include
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_negotiation">content negotiation</a> or simply using
redirects. Content negotiation is also a little bit complicated and requires the ability
to configure the web server. Redirects are simpler, but introduce two different
URIs which might be confusing.</p>

<p>With luck, the WHATWG will be persuaded not to break the web and we won’t have to
do any of these things. But there are options.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Removing XSLT from the browser</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/08/20-removing-xslt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/08/20-removing-xslt.html</id><published>2025-08-20T17:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/08/20-removing-xslt.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Removing XSLT from the browser</h1>

<p>The <a href="https://whatwg.org/">WHATWG</a> recently proposed to “remove
XSLT from the web platform”. This is not the
<a href="https://groups.google.com/a/chromium.org/g/blink-dev/c/zIg2KC7PyH0">first attempt</a>.
There’s a long discussion thread on the GitHub issue for the
<a href="https://github.com/whatwg/html/issues/11523 ">current proposal</a>,
including a lot of pushback. The same is true of the
<a href="https://github.com/whatwg/html/pull/11563">related issue</a>
to “remove mentions of XSLT from the html[sic] spec”.</p>

<p>Whether the current attempt to deprecate XSLT in the browser succeeds, or
whether feedback from users will be sufficient to discourage them again, I don’t
know. Regardless of the outcome, it's clear that we are heading closer and
closer to a monoculture in web browsers.</p>

<p>Deprecating XSLT will break a lot of web pages. Thousands of Saxonica's pages,
and perhaps tens of thousands of others. It will break web pages that have been
quietly and usefully referenced by an unknown number of users for a couple of
decades. It will break web pages that are immutable, that are not, or can no
longer be, maintained because the projects have ended or the authors have died.
Things will be forever lost because tens of thousands of pages aren’t enough.</p>

<p>I’m sure there are technical arguments in favor of removing XSLT from the
browser, including arguments about code complexity or security. And I’m sure
there are economic arguments about the importance of investing resources where
they matter most, or at least in places offering the best return on investment.
None of these arguments show consideration for the health of the web as a
reliable, open set of technologies which can be easily used by individuals and
large corporations alike.</p>

<p>Of course, building web applications with XSLT 1.0 is a considerable challenge.
This is probably the main reason why most publishers delivering complex XML
documents have continued to use XSLT on the server, where the technology is
constantly refreshed, rather than sticking with a stagnant 25-year-old
client-side implementation. Many XSLT users would happily switch to using
client-side transformation if it were actively supported by the browser vendors,
including support for later versions of the standard, which offer much higher
productivity.</p>

<p>Saxonica publishes world-class implementations of XSLT for Java, C#, C, C++,
Python, and JavaScript. Our JavaScript implementation runs both in the browser
and on NodeJS. We support the current, modern standards and we’re actively
involved in developing those standards for the future. XSLT is the most
cost-effective solution for a wide range of practical use cases, and the size
and breadth of Saxonica's user base reflects this fact.</p>

<p>XSLT will continue to survive, and thrive, even if the WHATWG insists on
depriving web developers and users of the many advantages modern XSLT would
offer them.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Saxon 11.7 and 12.8</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-11.7-and-12.8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-11.7-and-12.8.html</id><published>2025-07-03T17:40:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-11.7-and-12.8.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>The accompanying release announcements for
<a href="saxon-11.7.html">Saxon 11.7</a> and
<a href="saxon-12.8.html">Saxon 12.8</a> describe those
releases in detail. This post summarizes why we decided that we
needed to release them both this week.</p>

<p>Some applications are known to use Saxon to run untrusted, user-submitted
stylesheets or queries. Running untrusted code always entails some risk. Saxon
provides two
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12/index.html#!configuration/config-features">features</a>
designed to help mitigate this risk: <code>ALLOWED_PROTOCOLS</code> and

<code>ALLOW_EXTERNAL_FUNCTIONS</code>. Setting <code>ALLOWED_PROTOCOLS</code>
can limit what resources a stylesheet or query can access; it can for example,
forbid access to file: URIs. The <code>ALLOW_EXTERNAL_FUNCTIONS</code> feature
can disable access to reflexive Java extension functions, some system
properties, and some other extension functions. (The remit of the
<code>ALLOW_EXTERNAL_FUNCTIONS</code> feature is a little wider than you might
expect.)</p>

<p>Unfortunately, we discovered a function in Saxon 11 and 12 that was not
adequately controlled by these features. In principle, a stylesheet or query
running in Saxon-PE or Saxon-EE could access the local filesystem even if the
<code>ALLOWED_PROTOCOLS</code> feature was set to forbid such access. The risk
is small: it only applies to untrusted code running in Saxon-PE or Saxon-EE (it
does not apply to Saxon-HE) on a system where reading from the local filesystem
would be deemed a risk. (We would encourage anyone running untrusted code to use
a sandboxed environment where there is no data on the filesystem that needs to
be protected from read access.)</p>

<p>Although we judge the risk to be small, At Saxonica, we take security
seriously and we are publishing maintenance releases of Saxon 11 and Saxon 12 to
close this gap. We urge anyone running untrusted stylesheets or queries under
Saxon-PE or Saxon-EE to move to version 11.7 or 12.8 immediately.</p>

<p>This bug is present in the Java, C#, C, C++, Python and PHP products. It is
not present in Saxon 10 (including the Saxon.NET 10) or in earlier releases. It
is not present in SaxonJS.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 12.8!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-12.8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-12.8.html</id><published>2025-07-03T17:35:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-12.8.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 12.8!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 12.8 maintenance release has been published.
This is a
maintenance release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that
<a href="saxon-11.7-and-12.8.html">fixes a security gap</a> and a few
other issues that have been addressed since 12.7 was released.</p>

<p>Saxon 12.8 was released on 3 July 2025. This release has been uploaded to the
usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub, and Maven, PyPi, and NuGet.
SaxonCS 12.8 is built with .NET 8.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the issue trackers
for
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bstatus_id%5D%5B%5D=3&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=103&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonJ and SaxonCS</a> or
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bstatus_id%5D%5B%5D=3&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=104&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonC</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/12.8">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>Python wheels for SaxonC (HE, PE, and EE) are available from
<a href="https://pypi.org/user/saxonica/">PyPI</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is available from our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<h2>Issues resolved</h2>

<p>In addition to the security issue, only a few other issues have been fixed;
our focus was on getting the security release out promptly.</p>

<h3>Issues in SaxonJ</h3>

<p>Only one additional issue was fixed in SaxonJ:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6804">6804</a>
    String index out-of-bounds in <code>parse-xml()</code></li>
</ul>

<h3>Issues in SaxonC</h3>

<p>A few small issues were fixed in SaxonC:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6835">6835</a>
    SaxonC PHP @@VERSION@@</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6830">6830</a>
    SaxonC HE 12.7.0 - PHP - XdmNode-&gt;getColumnNumber() returns the line number</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6823">6823</a>
    DocumentBuilder memory not deleted</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6803">6803</a>
    Please provide parseJsonFromString example</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6802">6802</a>
    Remove XdmAtomicValue::getStringValue</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6801">6801</a>
    PRIMITIVE_TYPE defined, but not used?</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6800">6800</a>
    Implement operator== for XdmItem or make it private</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6785">6785</a>
    Instructions in Python README for running pytest are missing the use of a pytest.ini</li>
</ul>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 12.8, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 11.7!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-11.7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-11.7.html</id><published>2025-07-03T17:30:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/07/saxon-11.7.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 11.7!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 11.7 maintenance release has been published.
This is a
maintenance release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that
<a href="saxon-11.7-and-12.8.html">fixes a security gap</a> and a number of
other issues that have been addressed since 11.6 was released.</p>

<p>Saxon 11.7 was released on 3 July 2025. This release has been
uploaded to the usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub,
Maven, and NuGet. SaxonCS 11.7 is built with .NET 8.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bstatus_id%5D%5B%5D=3&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=102&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">issue tracker</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/11.7">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is no longer distributed on SourceForge. It is now available from
our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation11">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 11.7, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing SaxonJS-HE 3.0.0-beta2!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/06/saxonjs-3.0.0-beta2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/06/saxonjs-3.0.0-beta2.html</id><published>2025-06-02T13:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/06/saxonjs-3.0.0-beta2.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing SaxonJS-HE 3.0.0-beta2!</h1>

<p>SaxonJS 3.0 is a major update to the SaxonJS product. In June 2025, we are
publishing a second preview release, version 3.0.0-beta2. This is a preview
release of the SaxonJS 3.0 HE (Home Edition) product. An EE (Enterprise Edition)
product is in the works.
</p>

<div>
<h2>New features in the beta2 release</h2>

<p>This release includes a few bug fixes from the first beta.
</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5923">5923</a>
   Provide a way to control event listener parameters</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6599">6599</a>
   Sequence interacts badly with try/catch</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6697">6697</a>
   Checksum checking in SaxonJS 3</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6742">6742</a>
   Untethered promises with SaxonJS 3.0.0-beta1</li>
</ul>

<p>Of these, the most consequential is probably 6697. In the course of fixing a
bug related to SEF files produced for SaxonJS 2, we introduced a bug where
SaxonJ 12.6 couldn’t produce SEF files for SaxonJS 3.0 beta1! That’s been fixed.
You can now produce SEF files for SaxonJS 3.0 beta2 with Saxon 12.6 or later.
(Unfortunately, you can’t produce SEF files for SaxonJS 3.0 beta2 with SaxonJ
12.5 or earlier!)
</p>

<div>
<h2>Getting started</h2>
</div>

<p>You can try out SaxonJS-HE 3.0 today, the packages have been uploaded to
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/">npmjs.com</a>: 
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/saxonjs-he">saxonjs-he</a>
and 
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/xslt3-he">xslt3-he</a>. You can also
download them <a href="https://downloads.saxonica.com/SaxonJS/3/index.html">our website</a>.</p>

<p>Our <a href="https://www.saxonica.com/saxonjs/documentation3/index.html">documentation
pages</a> have been updated.</p>

<p>Please report any issues that you encounter on <a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-js/issues">our issue tracker</a>.
</p>

</div>
</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 12.7!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/05/saxon-12.7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/05/saxon-12.7.html</id><published>2025-05-16T10:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/05/saxon-12.7.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 12.7!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 12.7 maintenance release has been published. This is a maintenance
release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that addresses a few significant
shortcomings in the Saxon 12.6 release.
</p>

<p>Saxon 12.7 was released on 16 May 2025. This release has been uploaded to the
usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub, and Maven, PyPi, and NuGet.
SaxonCS 12.7 is built with .NET 8.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the issue trackers
for
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bstatus_id%5D%5B%5D=3&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=101&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonJ and SaxonCS</a> or
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bstatus_id%5D%5B%5D=3&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=100&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonC</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/12.7">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>Python wheels for SaxonC (HE, PE, and EE) are available from
<a href="https://pypi.org/user/saxonica/">PyPI</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is available from our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<h2>Issues resolved</h2>

<p>The substantial changes in this release are:</p>

<ol>
<li>We’ve returned to supporting JDK 8 in 12.7. The decision to move to JDK 11
in 12.6 was intentional, but perhaps too eager. Fair warning: it is very
unlikely that Saxon 13 will be released with support for JDK 8.</li>
<li>We worked around a bug that caused the SaxonC products to fail under X86 emulation
on Windows/ARM. (The bug is that Windows emulation doesn’t support some modern
instructions that GraalVM was generating. We worked around it by turning down some
GraalVM optimizations in that environment.)</li>
</ol>

<h3>Issues in SaxonJ and SaxonCS</h3>

<p>These are just the release highlights, for a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bstatus_id%5D%5B%5D=3&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=101&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6547">6547</a>
    Resolved some schema loading performance regressions</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6771">6771</a>
    Restored JDK 8 compatibility to the class files</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6776">6776</a>
    Resolved a null pointer exception</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6778">6778</a>
    Fixed the class name in the javax.xml.validation.SchemaFactory service</li>
</ul>

<h3>Issues in SaxonC</h3>

<p>In addition to the X86 emulation problem, we resolved a few more issues in SaxonC.
For a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bstatus_id%5D%5B%5D=3&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=100&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6443">6443</a>
    Fixed a bug in Python PySaxonProcessor.make_atomic_value</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6522">6522</a>
    The documentation for Saxon\SchemaValidator is incorrect</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6525">6525</a>
    Fixed XdmNode::getChildren()</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6526">6526</a>
    Fixed xdmNode-&gt;axisNodes(3) on PHP</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6536">6536</a>
    Fixed segmentation fault with Python SaxonCHE 12.5</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6780">6780</a>
    Accepted suggestion to set sxn_environ values to NULL after allocation</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6781">6781</a>
    Fixed crash on Windows 11 under x86 emulation on ARM</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6787">6787</a>
    The setCatalogFiles method was missing from the C API</li>
</ul>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 12.7, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 12.6!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/05/saxon-12.6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/05/saxon-12.6.html</id><published>2025-05-02T15:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2025/05/saxon-12.6.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 12.6!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 12.6 maintenance release has been published. This is a maintenance
release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that addresses well over 100 issues
and feature requests reported since the Saxon 12.5 release.
</p>

<p>Saxon 12.6 was released on 2 May 2025. This release has been uploaded to the
usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub, and Maven, PyPi, and NuGet.
SaxonCS 12.6 is built with .NET 8.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the issue trackers
for
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=98&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonJ and SaxonCS</a> or
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=99&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonC</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/12.6">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>Python wheels for SaxonC (HE, PE, and EE) are available from
<a href="https://pypi.org/user/saxonica/">PyPI</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is available from our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<h2>Partial list of issues resolved</h2>

<p>This section is a subset of the complete list of resolved issues.
It’s curated to bring attention to the bugs that seem most likely to
impact customers. 
</p>

<h3>Issues in SaxonJ and SaxonCS</h3>

<p>In addition to the individual issues listed below, this release fixes
several issues related to streaming transformations and several issues
related to tracing.</p>

<p>For a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=98&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6748">6748</a>
    Updated xsl:array to track the evolving QT4CG specifications</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6746">6746</a>
    Resolved errors related to version ranges in xsl:use-package/@package-version</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6724">6724</a>
    Clarified limitations on importing schemas for reserved namespaces (such as fn:)</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6711">6711</a>
    Clarified how setting allowedProtocols to restrict parse-xml is handled</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6696">6696</a>
    Resolved a concurrency issue during lazy evaluation</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6688">6688</a>
    Fixed a bug where the coverage report from XSpec creates XML that is not well formed</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6682">6682</a>
    Resolved an issue in XSD uniqueness constraints vs. key constraints</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6679">6679</a>
    Fixed a bug where an incorrect variable was accessed when using xsl:iterate within xsl:accumulator</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6671">6671</a>
    Resolved an issue during schema load with multiple imports</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6652">6652</a>
    parse-xml no longer fails if the string it’s parsing begins with a BOM</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6621">6621</a>
    Clarified how reflexive extension functions and varargs work</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6597">6597</a>
    Fixed a bug where calling getBaseUri() in the Axiom tree model triggers infinite recursion</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6577">6577</a>
    Resolved an issue related to xsl:where-populated and namespace fixup</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6565">6565</a>
    Fixed a performance regression in DocumentFn with Java 12 or higher</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6544">6544</a>
    Fixed a bug where ID/IDREF attributes were not recognized when using the StAX parser</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6543">6543</a>
    Fixed a bug where whitespace text nodes were reported incorrectly when using a pull parser</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6537">6537</a>
    Fixed incorrect rounding of negative xs:double values</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6504">6504</a>
    Clarified how collection() and uri-collection() handle invalid URIs</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6502">6502</a>
    Fixed a bug where several invalid patterns were accepted</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6494">6494</a>
    Fixed a bug where whitespace text output disappeared when indenting</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6489">6489</a>
    Fixed Gizmo issue with prefix, precede, suffix, and follow commands</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6480">6480</a>
    Cardinality of sequences returned by extension functions are now validated</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6472">6472</a>
    Fixed a bug related to sort order in xsl:for-each-group in named templates</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6471">6471</a>
    Corrected the operator precedence of validate expressions</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6452">6452</a>
    Fixed round#2 and round-half-to-even#2 to give correct results on large negative integers</li>
</ul>




<h3>Issues in SaxonC</h3>

<p>In the SaxonC 12.6 release, we have included a compiled C++ API library
(.dll, .so, .dylib as appropriate) along with accompanying CMake files to
simplify integration into C++ applications. This is provided in addition to the
core SaxonC library, which continues to be cross-compiled using GraalVM.</p>

<p>To use SaxonC in a C++ project, users now only need the two compiled library
files and the header files—greatly reducing setup complexity. Integrating with a
project already using CMake is as simple as using FindPackage(SaxonCHE 12.6.0)
(Or SaxonCEE, or SaxonCPE, if using the EE or PE editions). A sample CMake
project is provided with the samples in the download ZIP.</p>

<p>This change applies only to the C++ API. It does not affect the PHP or Python extensions:</p>
<dl>
<dt>PHP</dt>
<dd>Installation instructions are included in the README file in the download
ZIP and also available in the online documentation.</dd>
<dt>Python</dt>
<dd>The extension is distributed as pre-built wheels via PyPI, making
installation straightforward using pip.</dd>
</dl>

<p>In addition to the individual issues listed below, this release fixes a
number of multithreading issues, encoding problems, and memory leaks. API
support has been added for getcwd, getProperty/getProperties, and
getJustInTimeCompilation on several objects. There have also been a number
of documentation improvements.</p>

<p>For a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=99&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6731">6731</a>
    Support adding properties to the Processor in the Saxon C API</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6695">6695</a>
    Fixed an issue related to creating maps of strings in Python</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6677">6677</a>
    Improve error messages associated with Xslt30Processor::compileFromString</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6676">6676</a>
    Support initial template invocation with a combination of tunnel and non-tunnel parameters</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6668">6668</a>
    Support setOutputFile() on SchemaValidator</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6657">6657</a>
    Fixed line and column numbers in PySaxonApiError message</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6656">6656</a>
    Fixed a bug where multiple calls to XdmNode.getParent() could leads to an exception</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6649">6649</a>
    Improved error message associated with an expired license</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6634">6634</a>
    Added support for getcwd and getProperties</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6628">6628</a>
    Fixed a bug where the copy constructor for Xdm objects failed</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6620">6620</a>
    Fixed a double-free bug in clearSettings</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6619">6619</a>
    Resolved missing calls to super constructors</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6618">6618</a>
    Fixed a bug where getDoubleValue crashed for text strings in XdmAtomicValue class</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6615">6615</a>
    Fixed a bug where isEmpty crashed for new empty XdmMap</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6614">6614</a>
    Fixed a bug where the XdmValue::XdmValue constructor crashed</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6606">6606</a>
    Fixed a bug related to cwd and static-base-uri() in XPath</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6605">6605</a>
    Fixed a bug in static-base-uri() when compiling a query from a string</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6575">6575</a>
    Resolved a bug where som exception messages were empty in the PHP API</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6573">6573</a>
    Added isMap, isArray and isFunction methods to the PHP API</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6562">6562</a>
    Fixed issues related to mapSize when casting XdmValue from parseJson to XdmMap</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6556">6556</a>
    Fixed a bug where the standardErrorOutputFile feature was ignored</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6539">6539</a>
    Support PyXdmMap and PyXdmArray on PySaxonProcessor.parse_json</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6475">6475</a>
    Fixed a bug where the PySchemaValidator did not handle an XdmNode input correctly</li>
</ul>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 12.6, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>21st Anniversary Flash Sale!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/02/06-flash.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/02/06-flash.html</id><published>2025-02-06T14:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2025/02/06-flash.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>21<sup>st</sup> Anniversary Flash Sale!</h1>

<img class="sale" src="/img/saxon21.jpg" alt="Saxon at 21 Flash Sale banner"/>
<p>Saxonica was incorporated twenty-one years ago, in February 2004. To
celebrate, we’re having a flash sale. For one weekend only, a Saxon license
is just <span title="Base 2 is just like base 10… if you're missing 8 fingers">£101.01</span>!<sup><a class="tandclink" href="#tandc">*</a></sup></p>

<p>A lot has changed since Michael Kay founded Saxonica. Our flagship Java
product has been joined by C, C++, C#, JavaScript, PHP, and Python products.
We’re now delivering applications and tools for three platforms across five
architectures. Our team has grown, and our business has evolved. But what hasn’t
changed is our dedication to being an industry-leading provider of XML
technologies.</p>

<p>The sale runs Friday evening (7 February 2025) through Monday morning, UK
time. With a savings of almost 75% off our regular price, this is your perfect
opportunity to hop aboard and join us for the next 21 years!</p>

<p id="tandc" class="fineprint"><sup>*</sup> Terms and conditions apply 😁:
limited to one single-user EE license purchased through our online shop.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing SaxonJS-HE 3.0.0-beta1!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/12/saxonjs-he-3.0.0-beta1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/12/saxonjs-he-3.0.0-beta1.html</id><published>2024-12-18T16:30:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/12/saxonjs-he-3.0.0-beta1.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing SaxonJS-HE 3.0.0-beta1!</h1>

<p>SaxonJS 3.0 is a major update to the SaxonJS product. In December 2024, it is
being published as a preview release, version 3.0.0-beta1. This is a preview
release of the SaxonJS 3.0 HE (Home Edition) product. An EE (Enterprise Edition)
product is in the works.
</p>

<div>
<h2>New features in the beta1 release</h2>

<p>This release includes a number of new features, with several more planned
before the final 3.0 release.
</p>

<div>
<h3>Promises</h3>

<p>SaxonJS 3 introduces new mechanisms for enabling asynchronous processing
using promises. A new instruction <code>ixsl:promise</code> is introduced which
can be used as a replacement for the existing <code>ixsl:schedule-action</code>
instruction.
</p>

<ul>
<li>The new instruction can now call any asychronous function to fetch any kind of
resource. Adding new kinds of resource is just a question of implementing new
functions (which can be user-written functions as well as system-supplied
functions). So if you want to fetch data from a SQL database, for example, you
can easily write a function to do that.</li>
<li>The machinery for handling asynchronous requests is now closely aligned with
JavaScript promises, both in terms of the conceptual design, and the
implementation. This makes it much easier to understand for users familiar
with the JavaScript processing model.</li>
<li>The mechanism takes advantage of XDM higher-order functions. (Note, however,
that it still “bends” the pure declarative approach of XPath by introducing
mutability. A promise, for example, is a mutable object, so you need to
exercise care for example if you bind it to a variable.)</li>
</ul>

<p>Note that for Node.js, run time use of ixsl:promise is an EE feature. So XSLT
stylesheets using <code>ixsl:promise</code> can be compiled to SEF with the XX
compiler in SaxonJS without a JS-EE license, and then run in the browser; but to
run such a stylesheet on Node.js requires SaxonJS-EE and a valid JS-EE license.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h3>JavaScript extension functions</h3>

<p>JavaScript developers have easy access to a huge variety of tools and
libraries distributed as JavaScript packages through <code>npm</code> and other
mechanisms. We want to make those libraries easily accessible for SaxonJS
developers too.
</p>

<p>In SaxonJS 3, you can define extension functions in JavaScript and call them
directly from XPath, both from <code>SaxonJS.XPath.evaluate</code> and from
within XSLT stylesheets running on SaxonJS in the browser or on Node.js.
</p>

<p>This opens up whole new horizons for SaxonJS developers.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h3>Smaller changes and improvements</h3>

<p>While a lot of our focus has been on larger improvements, a few less dramatic
features are also debuting in beta1.
</p>

<ul>
<li>Support XPath expressions (other than “.”) after ? in <code>xsl:result-document</code></li>
<li>New methods on <code>xsl:result-document</code>: <code>ixsl:replace-element</code>, <code>ixsl:insert-before</code>, and
<code>ixsl:insert-after</code></li>
<li>Improved support for following HTTP redirects</li>
<li>Improved support for accessing JavaScript objects with <code>ixsl:set-property</code>, <code>ixsl:json-parse</code>,
<code>ixsl:new</code>, <code>ixsl:apply</code>, <code>ixsl:call</code>, <code>ixsl:eval</code>, and <code>ixsl:get</code></li>
<li>Support the <code>escape-solidus</code> option when generating JSON.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>

<div>
<h2>New features coming soon</h2>

<p>Eager to publish a release, at this stage, we’ve opted only to publish the HE
version of SaxonJS 3.0 as beta1. More work is planned before the general
release, including SaxonJS 3.0 EE.
</p>

<div>
<h3>SaxonJS-EE</h3>

<p>SaxonJS-HE will remain a free product, but in 2025 we will also be introducing a
licensed version of SaxonJS, SaxonJS-EE. The licensed version will provide additional
features on Node.js (such as built-in EXPath and Saxon extension functions).
</p>

<p>The promises API run time will be a licensed feature on Node.js.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h3>Calling XSLT functions from JavaScript</h3>

<p>Many transformations, on XML and JSON, are easier to define in XSLT than in
JavaScript. XSLT has a rich vocabulary of instructions for describing, constructing,
and transforming data in a clear, descriptive, and functional way.
</p>

<p>We anticipate making those features more accessible to JavaScript developers by
allowing JavaScript to call functions defined in XSLT.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h3>Adding a SaxonJS.compile API</h3>

<p>The ability to construct an XSLT stylesheet and then compile it directly for
use in the current transformation is a powerful feature. A new API for doing this,
<code>SaxonJS.compile</code>, will be added in the general release.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Getting started</h2>
</div>

<p>You can try out SaxonJS-HE 3.0 today, the packages have been uploaded to
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/">npmjs.com</a>: 
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/saxonjs-he">saxonjs-he</a>
and 
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/xslt3-he">xslt3-he</a>. You can also
download them <a href="https://downloads.saxonica.com/SaxonJS/3/index.html">our website</a>.</p>

<p>Our <a href="https://www.saxonica.com/saxonjs/documentation3/index.html">documentation
pages</a> have been updated and a repository of short examples has been
published: <a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/SaxonJS3-demo">SaxonJS3
demo</a>.</p>

<p>We hope you’re as excited as we are and we look forward to your feedback. Please
report any issues that you encounter on
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-js/issues">our issue tracker</a>.
</p>

</div>
</div></content></entry><entry><title>Oops, we did it again</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2024/10/17-oops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2024/10/17-oops.html</id><published>2024-10-17T15:01:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2024/10/17-oops.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>As some of you have noticed, the SaxonJS
“<a href="../../2023/10/06-no-longer-supported.html">no longer supported</a>” bug
returned a few days ago. I’d have sworn that I removed that warning when we shipped
SaxonJS 2.6. But I’d also have sworn we would get 3.0 out before now. Maybe I’m
not very good at swearing.</p>

<p>That warning <em>has been</em> removed from
<a href="../../../announcements/2024/10/saxonjs-2.7.html">SaxonJS 2.7</a>, so
this issue won’t surface again next October.</p>

<p>Apologies for not getting a maintenance release out sooner. We really should
have. Focus has been on SaxonJS 3.0, which is still coming along nicely, but
there were a number of bug fixes in SaxonJS 2.x that we could have shipped
months ago.</p>

<p>My expectation is that we’ll ship some sort of beta test version of SaxonJS
3.0 “real soon now” and Saxon 12.6 to fix
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6487">the SEF bug</a> in 12.5 shortly
before or after that.
</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing SaxonJS 2.7!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/10/saxonjs-2.7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/10/saxonjs-2.7.html</id><published>2024-10-17T15:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/10/saxonjs-2.7.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing SaxonJS 2.7!</h1>

<p>The SaxonJS 2.7 maintenance release has been published. This is a
maintenance release for NodeJS and the browser. It fixes a number of bugs.
(Including <a href="/norm/2023/10/06-no-longer-supported.html">that one</a>
about the spurious warning message. Again.)</p>

<p>Highlights include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/4991">#4991</a>: Support JSON indentation in xml-to-json</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5540">#5540</a>: Namespace context is reset before each XSLT transformation</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5743">#5743</a>: Text nodes are no longer lost in xsl:catch instruction</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6234">#6234</a>: Corrected the behavior of a map called as a function</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6318">#6318</a>: Fixed an error in parsing regular expressions</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6352">#6352</a>: Resolved a performance issue introduced in SaxonJS 2.6</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6393">#6393</a>: Fixed a string/number comparison bug</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6418">#6418</a>: Improve behavior when attempting to use IXSL extensions on Node.js</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6516">#6516</a>: Fixed some XPath parsing errors related to uncommon expressions (like <code>/[x]</code>)</li>
</ul>

<p>For a complete list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-js/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=c&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_10&amp;op%5Bcf_10%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_10%5D%5B%5D=97&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">issue tracker</a>
on the Saxonica support site.</p>

<p>SaxonJS 2.7 was released on 17 October 2024. This release has been
uploaded to the usual locations on the Saxonica website and the NPM
repository.
For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/saxon-js/documentation2/index.html">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<div class="note">
<p>Note: Saxon 12.5 won’t create SEF files that can be used with SaxonJS 2.x.
This is a <a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6487">known bug</a> that will
be fixed in Saxon 12.6. Saxon 12.4 and earlier versions will make SEF files that
SaxonJS 2.x can use.</p>
</div>

<p>If you encounter any issues with SaxonJS 2.7, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-js/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Packaging SaxonJS for the browser</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2024/08/16-packaging.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2024/08/16-packaging.html</id><published>2024-08-16T15:20:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2024/08/16-packaging.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>Over the years, there have been several requests to improve the way that
SaxonJS is packaged for the browser. In the run up towards SaxonJS 3.0 (real
soon now, I promise), I’ve spent a few hours trying to see if that’s possible.</p>

<p>For SaxonJS on Node.js, things seem to be working the way users expect. You
can install SaxonJS, and <em>xslt3.js</em>, the command-line XSLT processor,
with <code>npm install</code>. Then you can use them as you would other Node.js
modules and applications.</p>

<p>For the browser, things are a little less clear.</p>

<p>I’ll start out by observing that SaxonJS is a large(ish) collection of mostly
plain JavaScript files. There are a mixture of techniques used, as you might
expect from a code base that stretches back seven or eight years (roughly ∞ in
JavaScript years). This code is compiled by the <a href="https://developers.google.com/closure/compiler">Closure Compiler</a> to
produce the release artifacts.</p>

<div class="aside">
<p><em>Aside:</em> Producing TypeScript instead of JavaScript is almost certainly
impractical. And
the answer to the question, “can you make it an ESM module?” appears to be “no”. But
maybe I’m wrong?</p>
</div>

<p>Almost anything is <em>possible</em> in software,
but there some things are probably <em>impractical</em> because of how SaxonJS
is built.
</p>

<p>What I’ve come to realize after several hours is that I
don’t actually understand what problem I’m trying to solve. That usually makes
problems harder.</p>

<p>For example, it would be easy to package the browser versions of the SaxonJS
libraries into the <code>saxon-js</code> <em>npm</em> package. That would allow
you to use <code>npm install</code> to install it. Once installed, you could
refer to it in HTML like this:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;script src="node_modules/saxon-js/SaxonJS3.rt.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</code></pre>

<p>That’s a non-zero usability improvement over downloading the browser release
yourself and adding it to your project, but it’s an <em>awfully small</em>
improvement. So small, that I conjecture that the request to “put it in the npm
package” means more than that. But I don’t know what more.</p>

<p>Another request that’s come up a couple of times is whether we should provide
a version that’s been packaged up with <em>webpack</em>. Well. Okay. I spent
a bit of time on that and eventually I managed to get</p>

<pre><code>npx webpack --config webpack.config.js</code></pre>

<p>to take <code>src/SaxonJS3.js</code>, chew on it for a while, and produce
<code>dist/SaxonJS3.js</code>. That was a little, uh, underwhelming. I started
with a JavaScript library that I could load in the browser and ended with…a
different one, I guess?</p>

<p>Then there are suggestions that instead of <em>webpack</em> I should be
trying <em>vite</em> or <em>bun</em> or something else and do I also need
<em>browserify</em>? I don’t know.
I’m about to give up, at least in the short term, but before I do, I thought
I’d see if anyone out there can tell me what I’m missing.</p>

<p>If you would like to see SaxonJS for the browser packaged up in some
different way, can you tell me how? And why? A small test case would be ideal:
something that isn’t too complicated, that doesn’t work with SaxonJS as it’s
distributed today, that would work if we packaged it in some other way.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 12.5!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/07/saxon-12.5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/07/saxon-12.5.html</id><published>2024-07-02T11:30:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/07/saxon-12.5.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 12.5!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 12.5 maintenance release has been published. This is a
maintenance release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that fixes a
number of issues reported since previous Saxon 12.4 releases.
</p>

<p>Saxon 12.5 was released on 1 July 2024.
This release has been
uploaded to the usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub, and
Maven, PyPi, and NuGet. SaxonCS 12.5 is built with .NET 6. This
release includes SaxonC and Python releases for the ARM 64
architecture as well as X86-64 architecture.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the issue trackers
for
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=96&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonJ and SaxonCS</a> or
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_3&amp;op%5Bcf_3%5D=%7E&amp;v%5Bcf_3%5D%5B%5D=12.5&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonC</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/12.5">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>Python wheels for SaxonC (HE, PE, and EE) are available from
<a href="https://pypi.org/user/saxonica/">PyPI</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is available from our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<h2>Partial list of issues resolved</h2>

<p>This section is a subset of the complete list of resolved issues.
It’s curated to bring attention to the bugs that seem most likely to
impact customers. 
</p>

<h3>Issues in SaxonJ and SaxonCS</h3>

<p>For a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=96&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.</p>

<ul>

<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6450">6450</a>
    CollectionFinder parsesd ALLOWED_PROTOCOLS incorrectly</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6449">6449</a>
    SaxonCS failure when using collection function to pull a collection catalog file over HTTP(S)</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6448">6448</a>
    Saxon-HE 12.4J has wrong column number in trace, unlike Saxon-EE</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6446">6446</a>
    Improved performance of XQuery group by some circumstances</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6435">6435</a>
    Resolve concurrency issue in the use of accumulators behind the scenes in xsl:for-each</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6428">6428</a>
    Output of xsl:on-non-empty changes when using TraceListener</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6426">6426</a>
    fn:matches surprisingly returns false for fn:matches("AB", "^(.*)+B")</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6420">6420</a>
    -Tout filename not used when set on command line</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6419">6419</a>
    Union of nodes in a Template Match produces wrong output in Trace</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6415">6415</a>
    Improved results for trace of an unreferenced XSLT variables</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6407">6407</a>
    Tree Model option -tree seems to be ignored for initial source documents</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6406">6406</a>
    A collection cannot contain the same document more than once</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6405">6405</a>
    Improve saxon:column-number() for text nodes not inside xsl:text</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6394">6394</a>
    Resolve "Duplicate definition of global variable" exception when using compileLibrary on modules which import a common module</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6386">6386</a>
    Resolve inadvertant backwards incompatibility in some uses of Configuration#setFeature</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6381">6381</a>
    set_unprefixed_element_matching_policy(1) doesn't seem to work</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6380">6380</a>
    Internal error when match pattern invoked by xsl:next-match refers to global variable</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6378">6378</a>
    Resolved problem with tracing a variable declared abstract</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6377">6377</a>
    Resolved exception that could be thrown by format-time in some circumstances</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6370">6370</a>
    XSD based validation finds a validation throws NullPointerException when trying to generate a validation report</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6365">6365</a>
    Fixed bug where Gizmo could fail if no license was provided</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6363">6363</a>
    Incorrect result comparing untypedAtomic value to NaN</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6348">6348</a>
    Fixed multi-threading bug related to xsl:result-document operating asynchronously </li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6340">6340</a>
    Fixed exception that sometimes arose when using saxon:capture="yes" in an accumlator rule</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6339">6339</a>
    Describe fix and workaround for ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException in saxon:transform() </li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6313">6313</a>
    Static type error from fn:remove()</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6302">6302</a>
    Improved trace output when the transform function is used</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6286">6286</a>
    Resolved problem where $connection?close() could throw an error</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6279">6279</a>
    Incorrect optimization of generate-id() comparisons</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6256">6256</a>
    function-name returns an empty sequence for node-name#0, string#0 and more?</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6183">6183</a>
    Improved documentation for debugging errors when using "fallback=no" on UCA collation</li>
</ul>

<h3>Issues in SaxonC</h3>

<p>Memory management in SaxonC, PHP, and Python has been greatly improved. This resolved
a number of issues (<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6338">6338</a>,
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6349">6349</a>,
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6357">6357</a>,
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6396">6396</a>, and
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6397">6397</a>). In addition, the following
issues were resolved. (For a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_3&amp;op%5Bcf_3%5D=%7E&amp;v%5Bcf_3%5D%5B%5D=12.5&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.)</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6439">6439</a>
    Fixed bug in Python extension that could cause an AttributeError on PyXdmFunctionItem</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6402">6402</a>
    Added <code>clearXslMessages</code> to clear accumulated xsl:message messages</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6401">6401</a>
    Resolved bug when setting a filename on an executable in Python</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6372">6372</a>
    Updated build to include all character sets (will enable Windows-1252 encoded XML files to be parsed on Linux)</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6360">6360</a>
    Fixed bug where setOutputFile did not work with transformToFile()</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6356">6356</a>
    Fixed argument count error in executable in PHP</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6351">6351</a>
    Added methods for getting the line and column number of a node</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6342">6342</a>
    Fixed bug where in compileFromAssociatedFile PHP might fail</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6341">6341</a>
    Support try/catch in PHP for underlying parse errors</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6336">6336</a>
    Fixed bug when passing array values as parameters in Python</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6327">6327</a>
    Fixed bug where an empty XdmValue in Python might throw a TypeError</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6297">6297</a>
    Fixed build issue on CentOS 7</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6276">6276</a>
    Fixed bug where proc.version did not include the patch version</li>
</ul>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 12.5, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing SaxonC 12.4.2!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/01/saxonc-12.4.2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/01/saxonc-12.4.2.html</id><published>2024-01-26T10:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2024/01/saxonc-12.4.2.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing SaxonC 12.4.2!</h1>

<p>A SaxonC 12.4.2 maintenance release has been published. This
release fixes several issues:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6197">6197</a> A segmentation fault in the PHP extension</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6273">6273</a> A change in the way whitespace is handled in filenames</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6274">6274</a> An problem with the “encoding” keyword in the python saxon processor</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6277">6277</a> A build configuration issue for the SaxonC HE Python processor</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6288">6288</a> A build issue for the SaxonC PHP extension</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6294">6294</a> A segmentation fault parsing JSON</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6301">6301</a> A compile error related to memory allocation with some C++ compilers</li>
<!--
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6304">6304</a> An issue when using multiple threads from the Python processor</li>
-->
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6306">6306</a> Unreleased memory in the Python processor</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6324">6324</a>  A segmentation fault in the Python extension</li>
</ul>

<p>Some efforts have also been made to improve the way dynamic
libraries are referenced when using the C/C++ APIs directly. These
changes are reflected in the builds and in the scripts that compile
the “command” and “samples” applications.</p>

<p>In brief: on macOS, the dynamic library can be accessed through
<code>@rpath</code> and on Linux, the dynamic library can be placed in a standard
location or accessed with the <code>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code> environment variable.
On Windows, apparently the standard practice is to place the DLL in the same
directory as the executable.</p>

<p>For a more complete list of what’s new in 12.4, please see the original
<a href="../../2023/11/saxon-12.4.html">release announcement</a> and the
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/saxon-c/release-notes.xml">SaxonC release notes</a>
on the main website.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing SaxonC 12.4.1!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/12/saxonc-12.4.1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/12/saxonc-12.4.1.html</id><published>2023-12-01T14:50:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/12/saxonc-12.4.1.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing SaxonC 12.4.1!</h1>

<p>A SaxonC 12.4.1 maintenance release has been published. This
release fixes <a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6268">a build
error</a> on the Windows platform and includes one additional
patch.</p>

<p>I’m an ardent believer in build automation and reproducibility
through scripting. We’ve made a lot of progress in this area, but
Windows is still a bit “hands on.” Problem is, it was my hands and I
messed up.</p>

<p>A while back, we considered upgrading to a newer version of
GraalVM. In the course of testing that, I upgraded the version on the
Windows build machine. But ultimately, we decided not to make that
upgrade.</p>

<p>Despite having an explicit note in my release checklist:</p>

<ul>
<li>☑ Check the version of GraalVM</li>
</ul>

<p>I missed it on the Windows box. A lot of good detective work went
into trying to figure out what was going on, but in the end, just
building with the “right” version of GraalVM fixed it. Apologies to
the team and everyone else for that.</p>

<p>The 12.4.1 release also includes a
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6182">partial fix</a> for
issues relating to UTF-8 string-based C API functions. Unfortunately,
a more complete fix was deemed too risky for what was otherwise an
“emergency” release. That fix will have to wait for next time.</p>

<p>For a more complete list of what’s new in 12.4, please see the original
<a href="../11/saxon-12.4.html">release announcement</a>.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 12.4!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/11/saxon-12.4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/11/saxon-12.4.html</id><published>2023-11-29T18:30:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/11/saxon-12.4.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 12.4!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 12.4 maintenance release has been published. This is a
maintenance release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that fixes a
number of issues reported since the Saxon 12.3 release.
(Note: A <em>12.4.1</em> maintenance release of SaxonC
<a href="../12/saxonc-12.4.1.html">was published</a> on 1 December 2023.)
</p>

<p>Saxon 12.4 was released on 29 November 2023.
This release has been
uploaded to the usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub, and
Maven, PyPi, and NuGet. SaxonCS 12.4 is built with .NET 6. This
release includes SaxonC and Python releases for the ARM 64
architecture as well as X86-64 architecture.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the issue trackers
for
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=95&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonJ and SaxonCS</a> or
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_3&amp;op%5Bcf_3%5D=%7E&amp;v%5Bcf_3%5D%5B%5D=12.4&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">SaxonC</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/12.4">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>Python wheels for SaxonC (HE, PE, and EE) are available from
<a href="https://pypi.org/user/saxonica/">PyPI</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is available from our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<h2>Partial list of issues resolved</h2>

<p>This section is a subset of the complete list of resolved issues.
It’s curated to bring attention to the bugs that seem most likely to
impact customers. 
</p>

<h3>Issues in SaxonJ and SaxonCS</h3>

<p>For a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=95&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5792">5792</a>
    ICU spellout numbering</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5896">5896</a>
    Intermittent failure in multi-threading with XSLT</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5914">5914</a>
    Performance regression in SaxonJ 12, searching for context properties</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5949">5949</a>
    A resource loaded via the resolver vs one loaded "directly" is a different source with different options</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6049">6049</a>
    Does XQueryEvaluator for SaxonCS lack the API to set an ErrorReporter?</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6082">6082</a>
    Saxon 12 XQuery: Issue with compile-time error checking</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6090">6090</a>
    Performance regression SaxonCS 12</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6094">6094</a>
    saxon:eval and saxon:expression no longer available with Saxon 12</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6116">6116</a>
    UncheckedXPathException and missing error codes in output with Saxon-HE 12J</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6117">6117</a>
    Transformation using memo functions fails if the source is an XdmDocument.asSource()</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6128">6128</a>
    Unwanted diagnostic output when validating notations</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6130">6130</a>
    No error is reported for <code>schema-element(*:foo)</code></li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6131">6131</a>
    Unexpected function call triggers cardinality check and error</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6146">6146</a>
    Relative URI resolution in XQuery vs XSLT</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6147">6147</a>
    Incorrect fingerprint for XML_SPACE_TYPE</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6148">6148</a>
    xsi:type and xsi:schemaLocation on same element</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6149">6149</a>
    $connection?close() throws NullPointerException</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6153">6153</a>
    XSD blockDefault effect on complex types</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6157">6157</a>
    xsl:array instruction does not perform fallback processing</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6158">6158</a>
    Errors in xsl:fallback not detected</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6159">6159</a>
    sql:query() throws NullPointerException when retrieving a column with null value</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6160">6160</a>
    Key type in a MapTest cannot be a union type</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6161">6161</a>
    ReportingSingletonIterator.next throws NullPointerException - race condition</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6165">6165</a>
    Spurious template rule ambiguity reported</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6166">6166</a>
    Public fields in a Java instance object cannot be accessed from XSLT</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6167">6167</a>
    Enclosing modes do not work with JIT enabled</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6168">6168</a>
    mode="#all" failures with JIT enabled</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6176">6176</a>
    Failure to test for UncheckedXPathException</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6186">6186</a>
    IndexOutOfBounds exception during stylesheet compilation when package is overridden</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6196">6196</a>
    Functions of wrong arity: arguments → parameters</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6198">6198</a>
    SCM export fails for a schema containing namespace prefixes in an XPath expression</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6199">6199</a>
    SCM export/import sometimes fails for an <code>xs:alternative</code></li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6201">6201</a>
    configuration file: option for unparsed text URI Resolver</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6202">6202</a>
    Invalid attribute names in configuration files are ignored</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6207">6207</a>
    Filter expression not working properly</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6210">6210</a>
    Format of numbers generated by fn:json-to-xml</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6211">6211</a>
    Saxon return wrong error position in XPath expression</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6212">6212</a>
    Serializer tries to guess doctype from content and fails at it.</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6215">6215</a>
    SQL extension: returning the results of a join query</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6217">6217</a>
    Sliding windows: finished windows not output if windows that started earlier are unfinished</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6221">6221</a>
    Static error in XPath expression supplied to xsl:evaluate</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6225">6225</a>
    Significant performance problem for case insensitive regex matching under high concurrency</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6226">6226</a>
    Race condition initialising UnicodeBlocks class</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6230">6230</a>
    fn:transform doesn't use the resource resolver from the XPathContext</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6231">6231</a>
    Saxon does not recognise function annotations written using Q{uri}local syntax</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6232">6232</a>
    Error message: "An empty sequence is not allowed as the result of a call to map"</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6236">6236</a>
    Expected XPathException but got AssertionError 'No current component'</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6237">6237</a>
    HTTP redirection expects an absolute URI in the location field</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6238">6238</a>
    XPath error information is lost in XSLT</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6239">6239</a>
    Function conversion rules: xs:anyURI to xs:string conversion</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6249">6249</a>
    <code>xsl:evaluate/@context-item</code> expression is present, but evaluates to empty sequence</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6253">6253</a>
    Atomized item type for an array (test CastableAs667)</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6256">6256</a>
    function-name returns an empty sequence for node-name#0, string#0 and more?</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6257">6257</a>
    Gizmo quits after certain errors</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6258">6258</a>
    Repeated failures from unparsed-text() / unparsed-text-available()</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6260">6260</a>
    Operator || and fn:concat are not exactly equivalent</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6265">6265</a>
    NPE in net.sf.saxon.functions.Contains</li>
</ul>

<h3>Issues in SaxonC</h3>

<p>For a full list, see
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-c/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_3&amp;op%5Bcf_3%5D=%7E&amp;v%5Bcf_3%5D%5B%5D=12.4&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">the issue tracker</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6241">6241</a>:
    Python 3.12 wheels</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6195">6195</a>:
    Sources node objects not deleted in the C++ Schema validation samples</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6174">6174</a>:
    ICU localization is currently not supported</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6162">6162</a>:
    SaxonC does not accept multiple catalog files</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6144">6144</a>:
    PyXPathProcessor object has no attribute <code>thisxqptr</code></li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6143">6143</a>:
    White space in file path causing an error</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6118">6118</a>:
    parseJson API current not supported in SaxonC</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6109">6109</a>:
    Give SaxonC XPath API a counterpart to SaxonJ setUnprefixedElementMatchingPolicy</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6099">6099</a>:
    Import xslt package currently not available</li>
</ul>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 12.4, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing SaxonJS 2.6!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/10/saxonjs-2.6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/10/saxonjs-2.6.html</id><published>2023-10-13T15:45:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/10/saxonjs-2.6.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing SaxonJS 2.6!</h1>

<p>The SaxonJS 2.6 maintenance release has been published. This is a
maintenance release for NodeJS and the browser. It fixes more than a
dozen bugs (including <a href="/norm/2023/10/06-no-longer-supported.html">that one</a>
about the spurious warning message). Highlights include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5597">#5597</a>: ixsl:schedule-action fails without xsl:call-template</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5714">#5714</a>: Update documentation to mention the backtick escaping mechanism</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5739">#5739</a>: Space in string in text template not output as element content</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5761">#5761</a>: fn:transform called from XPath with simplified stylesheet gives an error</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5855">#5855</a>: map:merge with duplicates=combine gives wrong answer</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5925">#5925</a>: Dynamic function lookup runs very slowly</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/5974">#5974</a>: SaxonJS documentation does not address namespaces</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6037">#6037</a>: ixsl:schedule-action return objects</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6107">#6107</a>: Can't use namespaced attributes on the root element of the body of a SaxonJS http-request</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6134">#6134</a>: Partial function application call to function in ixsl namespace fails</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6216">#6216</a>: base-uri() value empty for documents async-loaded with ixsl:schedule-action/@http-request</li>
<li><a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6219">#6219</a>: base-uri(ixsl:page()) returns empty value</li>
</ul>

<p>For a complete list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-js/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_10&amp;op%5Bcf_10%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_10%5D%5B%5D=94&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">issue tracker</a>
on the Saxonica support site.</p>

<p>SaxonJS 2.6 was released on 13 October 2023. This release has been
uploaded to the usual locations on the Saxonica website and the NPM
repository.
For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/saxon-js/documentation2/index.html">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<p>If you encounter any issues with SaxonJS 2.6, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon-js/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>SaxonJS 2.5 ** NO LONGER SUPPORTED **</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/10/06-no-longer-supported.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/10/06-no-longer-supported.html</id><published>2023-10-06T13:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/10/06-no-longer-supported.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TL;DR">TL;DR</a>, you can
ignore the message.</p>

<p>Several folks have noticed that, since about yesterday, if you run
the SaxonJS 2.5 <code>xslt3</code> Node.js command line processor, it
prints a scary “no longer supported” message.</p>

<p>Sorry. Our bad. The message is only informative and has no effect
on the performance of the processor.</p>

<p>We support SaxonJS releases for at least a year and a while back
(far enough back that I can’t easily determine when from the
repository history), we confidently assumed that we’d always do a
release at least once a year. So when you got that message, it was to
encourage you to upgrade.</p>

<p>Except this year, we published a whole bunch of other releases,
embarked on SaxonJS 3.0, shifted our web infrastructure around, and
did a bunch of other things. What we didn’t do was publish SaxonJS 3.0
within a year, and because we were heads-down on that, we didn’t
notice that we hadn’t published a SaxonJS 2.6 release within a year
either.</p>

<p>(It’s all a little embarrassing.)</p>

<p>We’ve fixed a handful of bugs in SaxonJS 2.5 since we shipped it,
and we’ve identified a slightly larger handful that we’d like to
consider fixing before we ship a SaxonJS 2.6 release. But we will ship
it, as quickly as practical.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Looking forward</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/10/02-saxonica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/10/02-saxonica.html</id><published>2023-10-02T09:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/10/02-saxonica.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>As <a href="/mike/2023/10/eot.html">Mike says</a>, today is a big
day. It is an honour to be able to announce that I am taking on a new
role as CEO of Saxonica.</p>

<p>Let me start by offering huge congratulations and thanks to Mike and
Penny Kay, whose talent, commitment, and hard work have made Saxonica
into the successful company it is today.</p>

<p>I’m happy (and somewhat relieved!) to say that the Saxonica team
will continue to benefit from Mike’s experience for the foreseeable
future, as he moves to a new role as Director of Innovation. Working
part-time, Mike will continue to support customers and colleagues
alike, as well as ensuring that his in-depth knowledge of our code
base continues to be passed on to the rest of the Saxonica engineering
team, myself included!</p>

<p>Before I had the opportunity to join the company in 2020, I was
already an enthusiastic part of Saxonica’s user base. I know how
important our products are to our users; I <em>am</em> one of our users!</p>

<p>Working with this team of talented people to develop software that
makes a real contribution to the XML community has been a privilege.
Becoming Saxonica’s CEO is an even greater one. I am committed to
seeing Saxonica grow and prosper into the next decades, continuing the
reputation for excellence, innovation, and community-mindedness that
Mike has worked so hard to establish.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>XML Resolver 6.x SNAPSHOT</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/09/14-xmlresolver.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/09/14-xmlresolver.html</id><published>2023-09-14T14:55:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/09/14-xmlresolver.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>Under the hood, Saxon uses a “resolver” whenever it
attempts to load a document (a source document, stylesheet module,
unparsed text document, etc.). For the past few releases, the Java,
C#, and C products have been using resolvers based on the
<a href="https://xmlresolver.org/">XML Resolver APIs</a>.</p>

<p>I’ve been working on some improvements to those APIs. It’s likely
that the next releases of Saxon will be ship with XML Resolver
6.x.</p>

<p>If you’d like to
<a href="https://xmlresolver.org/6x-snapshot/">preview the planned changes</a>
and provide feedback about how they work in your applications, that’d
be grand.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>New infrastructure…</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/31-infrastructure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/31-infrastructure.html</id><published>2023-08-31T13:15:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/31-infrastructure.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>New infrastructure…</h1>

<p>Just FYI, we’ve moved some things around. Some of our web
infrastructure, the way
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/">www.saxonica.com</a>
and
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/">dev.saxonica.com</a>
are served, for example, has changed.
Plus we have some new infrastructure for
<a href="https://downloads.saxonica.com/">downloads</a>
and 
<a href="https://maven.saxonica.com/">Maven</a>.
</p>

<p>You aren’t supposed to notice. Or, at least, it isn’t supposed to
be broken. There are redirects in place for things we know moved and
a few very old things have fallen by the wayside.</p>

<p>If you see something that you think is broken, please tell us!</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>Announcing Saxon 11.6!</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/08/saxon-11.6.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/08/saxon-11.6.html</id><published>2023-08-24T13:30:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/announcements/2023/08/saxon-11.6.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>Announcing Saxon 11.6!</h1>

<p>The Saxon 11.6 maintenance release has been published. This is a
maintenance release for Java, C#, C/C++, PHP, and Python that fixes
almost 40 issues reported since the 11.5 release.</p>

<p>Saxon 11.6 was released on 24 August 2023. This release has been
uploaded to the usual locations on the Saxonica website, GitHub,
Maven, and NuGet. SaxonCS 11.6 is built with .NET 6.</p>

<p>For a list of the issues resolved in this release, please visit the
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;set_filter=1&amp;sort=id%3Adesc&amp;f%5B%5D=status_id&amp;op%5Bstatus_id%5D=c&amp;f%5B%5D=cf_6&amp;op%5Bcf_6%5D=%3D&amp;v%5Bcf_6%5D%5B%5D=93&amp;f%5B%5D=&amp;c%5B%5D=tracker&amp;c%5B%5D=status&amp;c%5B%5D=priority&amp;c%5B%5D=subject&amp;c%5B%5D=assigned_to&amp;c%5B%5D=updated_on&amp;group_by=&amp;t%5B%5D=">issue tracker</a>
on the Saxon support site.
</p>

<p>Download products:</p>

<ul>
<li>Binaries for PE and EE are available from our
<a href="http://www.saxonica.com/download/download_page.xml">download pages</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE is available on the
<a href="https://central.sonatype.com/artifact/net.sf.saxon/Saxon-HE/11.6">Maven Central
repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonJ-HE, PE, and EE can also be found on our
<a href="https://dev.saxonica.com/maven/">experimental Maven repository</a>.
</li>
<li>SaxonCS is available on
<a href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/SaxonCS">NuGet</a></li>
<li>Saxon-HE is no longer distributed on SourceForge. It is now available from
our open source
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/Saxon-HE/">GitHub repository</a>.
The GitHub repository also provides source code for those who need it.
</li>
</ul>

<p>For more details, please consult
<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation11">the documentation</a>.
</p>

<p>If you encounter any issues with Saxon 11.6, please
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/projects/saxon/issues">report them</a>
on our issue tracker.</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>ICU4J and SaxonJ EE</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/24-icu4j.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/24-icu4j.html</id><published>2023-08-24T12:15:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/24-icu4j.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<h1>ICU4J and SaxonJ EE</h1>

<p>We’ve recently discovered a small discrepancy in how we manage the
dependencies between <a href="https://unicode-org.github.io/icu/userguide/icu4j/">ICU4J</a>
and SaxonJ EE.</p>

<p>If you download the EE release from our website, you get a
distribution that includes SaxonJ EE, XML Resolver, ICU4J, and JLine
(used by Gizmo). The manifest in the SaxonJ EE jar file puts those
additional dependencies on your classpath automatically.</p>

<p>If you get the EE release from our Maven repository, ICU4J is an
<em>optional</em> dependency. So Maven won’t automatically put it on
your classpath. That’s the discrepancy.</p>

<p>Saxon EE will function without ICU4J, so it is technically
optional. I’m unsure which would be better: making it optional in both
places or non-optional in both places. Having it different certainly
seems like the worst choice and we should fix it.</p>

<p>In the short term, if you’re using Saxon EE and you want the
collations supported by ICU4J, make sure you’re also arranging for
ICU4J to be on your classpath.</p>

<p>We discovered this in the course of examining issue
<a href="https://saxonica.plan.io/issues/6183">#6183</a>. For slightly
complicated reasons involving our type hierarchy, if ICU4J is missing,
you can get an error message that suggests you’re running Saxon HE
even when you’re running EE. We’ll fix that too.
</p>

</div></content></entry><entry><title>XML doclet</title><link href="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/16-xmldoclet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><id>https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/16-xmldoclet.html</id><published>2023-08-16T10:00:00Z</published><content type="xhtml" xml:base="https://blog.saxonica.com/norm/2023/08/16-xmldoclet.html"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p>Historically, we’ve used a customized version of
<a href="https://jeldoclet.sourceforge.net/">JELDoclet</a> to generate
XML from Javadoc. We use the XML to construct parts of our website.
The Javadoc APIs used by JELDoclet (and all of the other
Javadoc-to-XML doclets that I could lay my hands on) have been deprecated as of
Java 9 and will eventually be removed from the JDK.</p>

<p>On a whim last weekend, I took a stab at simply rebuilding an XML
doclet on top of the new Javadoc APIs. You can find the results of that
effort in the <a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/xmldoclet">xmldoclet</a> repository.
</p>

<p>It’s only version 0.1.0, but I think it’s broadly functional. It
handles all of the sources I’ve thrown at it, including the Saxon Java
products which are fairly large and complex. If you try it out and
discover that it produces output that seems incomplete or incorrect, please
<a href="https://github.com/Saxonica/xmldoclet/issues">open an issue</a>.</p>

<p>I can’t say I’m especially fond of the Javadoc APIs. In particular,
although you need to know what imports a class has in order to
correctly resolve the names of types, the public APIs provide no
access to that information. In the end, I applied an old maxim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>If brute force doesn’t work, you’re not applying enough brute force.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I simply included the Java parser that we use for the transpiler and 
parse the sources myself.</p>

<p>Comments most welcome…</p>

</div></content></entry></feed>